Pier Family papers, Inclusive:1835-1997, undated, Bulk: 1862-1888
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Pier Family papers
Inclusive:1835-1997, undated, Bulk: 1862-1888
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3250
Lanigan, Jr., William F.
1 document box
The Pier Family papers contain transcriptions of letters written by Samuel Bradford Pier during the Civil War, color photocopies of members of the Pier family, genealogical information, photocopies of clippings, programs, and other materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Excellent.
Biography/Profile
James Bradford Pier (1813-1888) and Lucy Merry Pier (1814-1897), first members of the Pier family to arrive in Texas, settled in Austin County in 1835. James Pier served in the Texian army in the Texas Revolution, afterwards returning to the Pier homestead in Austin County. James and Lucy Pier had five children: Lucy Eliza Pier Cochran (1837-1880), Sarah Charlotte Pier Wiley (1840-1920), William Henry Pier (1843), Samuel Bradford Pier (1844-1914), and Julia Louise Pier (1847).
Both James and his son Samuel Bradford Pier joined the Confederate army during the Civil War. While James was stationed on the home front to watch prisoners at Hempstead, Texas, Samuel went to the battlefront, first as a private in Company G, 9th Texas Infantry, and later as a corporal in the 13th Texas Cavalry Battalion. Both men survived the war, with James passing away in 1888 and Samuel in 1914. They are both buried, along with other members of the Pier family, in several cemeteries in Austin County, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Pier Family papers contain materials from several generations of the Pier family, with most documents created by either James Bradford Pier or Samuel Bradford Pier.
Within letters and legal documents dating from 1834 to 1914 there are letters from Samuel to his wife while he was fighting in the Civil War. Some of those letters have been transcribed. There is a large folder of copied photographs, mostly Pier family members. A family member named Emma recorded family information in her Bible, printed in 1870. A copy of the related pages appears in this collection with dates from 1844 to 1902. A copy of an autograph album Samuel's uncle R. O. Pier gave him for Christmas 1859 also appears in this collection with signatures and notes dated 1859 to 1865. The clippings in this collection are largely family obituaries and are from the 1880s through the 1970s with many undated and in no particular order. Printouts from genealogical services and other collected family information also can be found in this collection. Family members James Bradford and Lucy Merry Pier were honored by the Daughters of the Republic of Texas with grave markers and a ceremony in 1986 as part of Texas Sesquicentennial celebrations. Information about this event and a historical paper written about this family by eighth grader Billy Lanigan can be found in this collection.
Arrangement
The Pier Family papers were arranged in folders with titles and no date ranges. Folder titles were mostly retained in the current round of processing. Presently, the collection is arranged in two series: Family Materials and II. Research Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3250. Acquired 1997-02-00
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Sarah C. Pier Wiley papers, Inclusive: 1838-1868, Bulk: 1853-1865
Related references
American Civil War Research Database. "Soldier Data: S.B. Pier." Alexander Street Press, LLC. Accessed 2020 June 26.
Find A Grave, Inc. "James Bradford Pier." Memorial #50647722. Databases. Accessed 2020 June 26.
Find A Grave, Inc. "Samuel Bradford Pier." Memorial #68061427. Databases. Accessed 2020 June 26.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Confederate States of America. Army. Texas Cavalry Battalion, 13th.
Places
Texas -- Genealogy.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Correspondence.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographs.; Programs (Publications).; Transcriptions (documents).
- Family Materials, 1835-1974, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Excellent.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence, financial bills and receipts, clippings, genealogy documents from the Family Bible, and photographs. The photographs are labeled with names and often with dates. This series is in excellent condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Correspondence, General, 1835-1881 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Samuel Bradford Pier, 1862-1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial, 1868-1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Album, 1859-1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family Bible, 1892-1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1888-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Research Materials, 1984-1997; 2
  This series contains programs, an essay about the Pier family, and various genealogy worksheets. This series is in excellent condition.
  - Genealogy Materials, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Essay, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)